Guide to the Eugene E. Barnett Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III. Chronological File, 1910-1970
  - 1937
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      (Including: Reports on Japanese atrocities in China (Rape of Nanking - report). Relief work - Y news - Eugene Epperson Barnett visit to South America (Lima, Peru), Personal letters ... to Hollis Wilbur (mostly China Y problems). Kiang Wen-han report on visit to Japan. Letter from Mrs. Frank Rawlinson, etc. Pamphlet - New Life Movement.)
    - From Chinese Recorder (January-March 1937) (Box 9)
      ("What the Y.M.C.A Has Contributed to the Chinese Church" - T.T. Law. Translated by T.K. Woang from article in Chinese in Truth and Life Magazine October 1935 - also pamphlet)
  - 1938
    - Personal Letters--Eugene Epperson Barnett, mostly to Mrs. R.H.B. (Box 10)
      (In China, Hangchow captured by Japanese (December 24, 1937) - "heroic service" of "plucky foreigners" - Gene Tuwen, Vaneverer (sic), Clayton, Fairclough (CIM)…also in Nanking - George Fitch.)
    - Conversation with Paul Super on Poland - Polish Y. (Box 10)
    - Other Y material (Box 10)
    - Translation of Diary of Chinese Student "The Long March of the Students from Changsha to Kunming" (Box 10)
    - Reports of Y in Europe (Eugene Epperson Barnett) (Box 10)
    - YMCA World Service, 1938-1944 (Box 10)
      (These are filed with the 1944 material in the collection, and consist of reports via excerpts on Y work in various parts of world... projects by Hatch, Buck, etc.)
  - 1939
    - Letters--Eugene Epperson Barnett to Mrs. Robert Howsen Barnett (Box 10)
    - "War and Post War", 1939-1951 (Box 10)
      (These are filed with the 1951 material in the collection. They consist of excerpts from Eugene Epperson Barnett letters)
  - 1940
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Letters re: Visit to the Far East (Box 10)
    - Letters to Eugene Epperson Barnett from recipients of report on Far East (Box 10)
  - 1941
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Letter to John R. Mott (Box 11)
    - War Prisoners Aid, BSO organized (Box 11)
    - Japanese Christian Deputation (Box 11)
    - United China Relief (Box 11)
    - Letter to Mrs. Robert Howsen Barnett regarding a house bought at 203 Hartsdale Rd., White Plains, New York (Box 11)
  - 1942
    - World War II
      - General (Box 11)
      - Reports on Student Work, Chungking - from Kiang Wen-han (Box 11)
      - S.C. Lsung - report on Y - 3 month trip - S.E. (Box 11)
      - "Hopes for Post-War World" (Box 11)
      - The Y and the War Effort (Box 11)
    - Letters - mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett - mostly to family (Box 11)
      (Letter to McMullen "children" on "Hangchow Reunion" at 203 Hartsdale Road - 1st returnees on SS Gripsholm. News of the "Macs" - Hangchow under Japanese, etc.)
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Radio broadcasts and speeches (brief): World Service (references to China), Y, The Churches, USO and YMCA, Youth, War, and the Future, etc. (Box 11)
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Letters
      - To Henry DeWitt Barnett (in army) (Box 11)
      - To Arthur Doak Barnett (Box 11)
      - To Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) (Box 11)
      - To Oliver "children" (Box 11)
        (re: news from Shanghai via first Gripsholm arrivals)
      - To Robert Warren Barnett (Box 11)
    - Letters from Relatives (Box 11)
    - Letter from Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) to Shanghai friends, returned marked "service suspended", 1941 December 1 (Box 11)
    - A Few Clippings (Box 11)
  - 1943
    - World War II (Box 11)
    - Christian leadership in World (Box 11)
    - National Mission on World Order (findings of Federal Council of Churches) (Box 11)
    - YMCA (wartime emphases) (Box 11)
    - History of the New York City Y (Box 11)
    - Reports on China (Box 11)
    - Y wartime student work (Box 11)
    - Family letters (Box 11)
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett to Lakeland (Box 11)
    - Robert Warren Barnett (excerpts) from Kunming (China Theater) (Box 11)
    - Henry DeWitt Barnett from Australia (Box 11)
    - Arthur Doak Barnett from Okinawa (1943 ?) (Box 11)
    - Family and Personal (Box 11)
      (Mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett letters to: Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett); Henry DeWitt Barnett; to various persons and Mrs. New re: a young Chinese fiend of hers; Robert Warren Barnett; Lillian Smith (in Clayton) February 9th - congratulations on list of Honor Roll of Race Race Relations just announced... also on recent issues of South Today; to ‘Aunt’ Janie Uhlendorf Brown)
    - A few clippings (Box 11)
    - A few letters from friends (Mrs. New and Others) (Box 11)
    - Invitation to dinner for Eduard Benes, of Chzechoslovakia (Box 11)
  - 1942-1943
    - Reports on Y work in wartime China (Box 11)
      (from Chungking, Yunnan, Lanchow, Wong Kong with reports from all over China. These reports includes dates and details on places and conditions of interest)
  - 1938-1944
    - YMCA World Service (Box 12)
      (Includes reports or excerpts on YMCA workin various parts of the word, including work of the Hatches (agriculture) in India, of Buck (physical education), etc.)
  - 1944
    - Family Letters (Box 12)
      (Mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett - full of comment on national and world affairs as well as on family news (Robert Warren Barnett, Henry DeWitt Barnett - overseas; Arthur Doak Barnett; Eugenia B. Schultheis, Billy, Bobby)
    - Letters to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) (Box 12)
    - Letter from Dr. R.J. McMullen (Box 12)
    - Some interesting correspondence re: Cairo Conference between Eugene Epperson Barnett and a "Japanophile", Dr. William Axling (who disapproved Article 3 - taking colonies away from Japan) (Box 12)
    - Letter to T.S. Elliott - Stilwell recall (Box 12)
    - Speeches - Mostly Y (Box 12)
  - 1945
    - Family Letters (Eugene Epperson Barnett) (Box 12)
    - Y Debt
      (Material pertaining to clearing of Y debt in 1945)
      - Congratulatory correspondence (Box 12)
      - "Background", 1943 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence and facts re John D. Rockefeller contributions (Box 12)
      - Letter on debt-clearing (Box 12)
    - Speeches (Box 12)
      (Y, Church, USO, etc.)
    - Personal Correspondence to and from Eugene Epperson Barnett
      (includes letters to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett))
      - Re: declining membership on Congregational Executive Committee of General Council (Box 12)
      - Letters from Grace Service re: Jack's trial (Box 12)
      - Letter to C.L. Hsia re: situation in China post-war (Box 12)
      - From Mrs. Charles W. Tillette - Thanks for Eugene Epperson Barnett recommending her as Member for the U.N. General Assembly (Box 12)
      - Prisoner of War work (to persons inquiring about YMCA POW work) and re: accusation by Walter Winchell on radio (Box 12)
      - Hangchow Y (Box 12)
  - 1946
    - YMCA speeches; reports on conferences, meetings, etc. and correspondence (Box 13)
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Letters to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) (Box 13)
      (Includes of Tar Heel Daily (April 14), and conferring of honorary degrees at the University of North Carolina, circa 1939)
  - 1947
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett addresses to various groups after visit abroad (Box 13)
      (Includes on to Rotary Club, South Bend, Indiana, introduced by Paul Hoffman)
    - Dinner for Studer, Detroit Y. (Box 13)
    - Introducing Dr. Kohak of Czechoslovakia (Box 13)
    - Letter to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. on Y (Box 13)
    - Correspondence--Eugene Epperson Barnett to family and others: Cleveland Dodge, Harper Sibley, Kirtley Mather, Gerald Birks, Dr. John R. Mott (Box 13)
    - Letter from Arthur Doak Barnett from China, 1947 April (Box 13)
    - Personal Correspondence to and from Eugene Epperson Barnett (Box 13)
      (including letter from O.R. Magill from Winling, Shanghia on Y, and letter from Doak on China situation)
    - Letter from Hangchow Y re: now Social Room named for Eugene Epperson Barnett (Box 13)
    - Letters from England and Scotland, summer 1947 - Eugene Epperson Barnett to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) and others (Box 13)
    - Pamphlet (in Chinese): Report of Ninth National Conference of Association Secretaries of China (Hangchow - October 1947). Introduction in English. Includes Photographs. (Box 13)
  - 1948
    - Personal notes and letters - Eugene Epperson Barnett (Box 14)
      - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Box 14)
      - Mrs. Harper Sibley (Box 14)
      - Mrs. Maurice Moore (Box 14)
      - Henry Luce (Box 14)
      - Leighton Stuart (Box 14)
      - S.C. Leung (Box 14)
      - Athenagoras - on his election as Patriarch, Constantinople. (Box 14)
      - Family (Box 14)
    - Speeches and correspondence (Box 14)
    - Family letters - Eugene Epperson Barnett (Box 14)
    - Letters, mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) (Box 14)
  - 1949
    - Letters, mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) (Box 14)
    - Speeches, devotionals, etc. (Eugene Epperson Barnett) (Box 14)
    - "In Europe - July 1949". (Box 14)
      (Informal notes (on Displaced Persons, Expellees, Refugees, Y in Europe, Churches, etc.) )
    - List of persons receiving "In Europe - July 1949" Notes and correspondence in response (Box 14)
    - Family Letters (Box 14)
      (Includes a lists of subjects)
  - 1950
    - Letters (Box 15)
      (Mostly Eugene Epperson Barnett to Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett))
    - Clippings (Box 15)
  - 1951
    - Letters (Box 15)
    - War and Post War", 1939-1951 (Box 15)
      (Excerpts from Eugene Epperson Barnett letters beginning 1939-1951on the subject)
  - 1952
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett Reports (Box 16)
      (On visits to Rome, Athens, Turkey, including bibliographies, letters, schedules, etc.)
    - Eugene Epperson Barnett visits to Aleppo, Beirut, Jerusaem (Box 16)
      (Includes letters, speeches, schedules with expenses)
    - Arab-Israel…refugee question, etc. (Box 16)
  - 1952-1954
    - YMCA: The Senior Secretaryship (Box 16)
      (Duties, role, etc. - correspondence re: above over period of years, reports of statements, etc.)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 17)
    (Includes Plenary Session, International Committee, YMCA)
  - 1955
    - Greece--Eugene Epperson Barnett/Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Emerson Barnett) Visit (Box 18)
      (Includes lists of persons seen, letter, and a confidential report )
  - 1954-1956 (Box 18)
  - 1957
    - Personal Correspondence--Letters to and from friends, USA and abroad (Box 19)
  - 1953-1958--Speeches and Devotionals (Box 20)
  - 1958--Personal Correspondence to and from friends, colleagues Clippings, cards, etc. (Box 20)
  - 1957-1958--UNESCO (Box 20)
  - 1958-1964--UNESCO (Box 21)
  - 1959--Eugene Epperson Barnett Personal letters of condolence and congratulations, with replies (Box 21)
  - 1960
    - Personal Correspondence (Box 22)
      (Condolence and Congratulations)
  - 1959
    - Personal Correspondence to and from Eugene Epperson Barnett (Box 22)
    - Also memoranda, schedules, leaflets, resumes, etc. (Box 22)
  - 1957-1960--General Correspondence (Box 22)
  - 1962--Assembly of Foreign Division, National Council of Churches (at Atlantic City) (Box 22-23)
  - 1963-1966 (Box 24-26)
  - Circa 1967-1970 (Box 27-29)
- Series IV. Subject File
  - China and Communism
    - Chinese Communism (Box 30)
      - General (Box 30)
      - 1947-1950 (Box 30)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 31)
      - Christianity and Communism (Box 31)
      - China/US Relations (Box 31)
      - Communism- Miscellaneous (Box 32)
  - Churches and Christianity
    - Catholic Church (Box 33)
    - Church and State (Box 33)
    - Churches (Box 33)
    - Federal Council of (Box 33)
    - Churches Protestant (Box 33)
    - Crisis in History of Christianity in China (Box 33)
    - Protestant/Catholic Relations (Box 33)
    - Study: Church in East Asia, 1956 (Box 34)
    - Social Perspectives for Planning by Churches (Box 34)
    - Fundamentalism (Box 34)
    - Bible (Box 34)
    - Church, and Social Action (Box 34)
    - Politics in Religion (Congregational Church) (Box 34)
  - Conferences, 1950-1969 (Box 35-37)
  - Course and Class Notes
    - Emory, Vanderbilt, etc., 1907-1921 (Box 38)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1930 (Box 39)
    - Sunday School and Bible (Box 40-41)
  - Memoirs
    - As I Look Back
      - Manuscript. (Box 42)
      - Mimeograph (Box 43)
    - Autobiographical notes and vitae (Box 44)
  - Organizations and Affiliations
    - Methodist Church (Box 45)
    - Methodist Committee for Overseas Relief (Box 45)
    - National Committee on US/China Relations (Box 45)
    - National Council of Churches (Box 45)
    - National Council of Churches (Box 46)
    - Population Council (Box 46)
    - United Board of Christian Higher Education (Box 46)
    - UN Organizations (Box 46)
    - World Council of Churches (Box 46)
  - Personal Files
    - Address Lists; Awards (Box 47)
    - Diary/Date Books (Box 48)
    - Engagements; Expenses (Box 49)
    - Letters, miscellaneous (Box 50)
    - Friends (Box 51)
    - Greeting Cards (Box 51)
    - Happenings, 1968 (Box 51)
    - Jury Duty (Box 51)
    - Retirement (Box 51)
    - Writings: Articles, Book Reviews, Memoranda, Notes, Reports (Box 52)
  - Speeches (See Also: Chronological Files)
    - 1910-1968 (Box 53-54)
    - 1936-1959 (Box 55)
      (Duplicates)
    - Notes (Box 56)
  - Travel journals, reports, and correspondence
    - 1929-1955 (Box 57-61)
    - Notes (Box 62)
  - YMCA
    - Announcements (Box 63)
    - Biographical Sketches
      - General (Box 63)
      - E.E. Barnett (Box 63)
      - John R. Mott (Box 63)
      - C. Tobias (Box 64)
      - S. Brockman (Box 64)
    - Catholic Church/YMCA (Box 64)
    - Chinese YMCA (Box 64)
    - Church/YMCA Relations (Box 64)
    - Committees
      - Historical Library Committee (Box 65-66)
      - General (Box 67-68)
    - Constituency (Box 69)
    - Correspondence (Box 69)
    - Dodge Dinner (Box 69)
    - Extension Policies (Box 69)
    - Financing (Box 69)
    - History (Box 70)
    - International (Box 71)
    - Jerusalem YMCA (Box 72)
    - Leung, S.C. (Box 72)
    - Middle Atlantic States (Box 72)
    - NAM/YMCA Encounter, 1944 (Box 72)
    - National YMCA (Box 72)
    - Objectives (Box 72)
    - POW’s (Box 72)
    - Retirees (Box 72)
    - Religious Emphasis (Box 72)
    - Rockefeller, John D. (Box 72)
    - Special Projects, 1951 (Box 73)
    - US/USSR YMCA Exchange (Box 73)
    - Vatican Council (Box 73)
    - Washington DC YMCA (Box 74-75)
    - Wilson, Woodrow (Box 76)
    - World Alliance (Box 76)
    - World Service (Box 76)
    - Youth (Box 76)
    - Youth and Religious Questions (Box 76)
    - Miscellaneous and Printed materials (Box 77-78)
  - Miscellaneous Subject and Name File
    - America, Post World War II (Box 79)
    - Athenagoras (Box 79)
    - Arlington County (Box 79)
    - Beaver Conference Farm (Box 79)
    - Blue Ridge (Box 79)
    - Brinkley, Margaret B. (Box 79)
    - Chinese Religion (Box 79)
    - Cultural Crisis (Box 80)
    - Employed Officers Alliance (Box 80)
    - Foreign Students (Box 80)
    - Institutes (Box 80)
    - Manuscripts by others (Box 80)
    - Missions (Box 80)
    - Nipps, Anne (Box 81)
    - Peace Corps (Box 81)
    - People (Box 81)
    - Quotations (Box 81)
    - Race (Box 81)
    - Saito Fund (Box 82)
    - South (Box 82)
    - United Board of Christian Colleges in China (Box 82)
    - Walker Chapel (Box 82)
    - Wen, S.T. (Box 82)
    - World Brotherhood (Box 82)
    - World War II (Box 82)
    - Zia, H.L. (Box 82)
  - Photographs and Memorabilia (Box 83)
  - Printed Materials
    - China and Asia (Box 84)
    - Periodicals (Box 85)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 86-87)
- Series V: 1979 Addition to the Collection
  - Personal and Family Correspondence
    - 1905-1910 (Box 88)
    - 1910-1916 (Box 89)
    - 1917-1922 (Box 90)
    - 1923-1926 (Box 91)
    - 1927-1931 (Box 92)
    - 1932-1953 (Box 93)
    - 1954-1964 (Box 94)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 95)
    - R.H. Barnett (Box 96)
    - R.I. Barnett (Box 96)
    - H.G. Barnett (Box 96)
    - Get Well, 1956 (Box 96-97)
    - Bertha Smith Barnett (Mrs. Eugene Epperson Barnett) (Box 98-99)
    - 60th Anniversary, 1970 (Box 100)
    - 1940-1970 (Box 101-105)
    - Miscellaneous; mixed years (Box 106)
  - Memorials and Sympathy Letters, 1970 (Box 107)
  - Manuscripts and Documents (Box 108)
  - Manuscripts (Box 109)
    - Bible Class Notes (Box 109)
    - Notebooks, datebooks and journals (Box 109)
  - Subject and Miscellaneous Files (Box 110-111)
  - Printed and Memorabilia; Photographs (Box 112)
  - Card Files
    - Addresses (Box 113)
    - Library (Box 113)